all right all right well good evening everybody at six o'clock so i'm going to call the uh meeting of committees to order um mr harris we're going to start with the roll call of members and then i'll have some reminders and announcements at the top of the meeting mr harris let's commit here here this is here mr hirsch here president here uh councillor rayo's excuse this evening okay so a few reminders and announcements for council and everyone here's with us so please take a moment to silence your phones and your devices if you haven't done so already this meeting and its participants are being recorded so tonight we have meetings of committees of council to the advisor no general public comment periods during this meeting however committee chairs may call for comments from the public for legislative items which are bills and resolutions comments uh if there are any are limited to three minutes per speaker and please begin with your name and block of residence for our meeting minutes as you may have noticed counselors and attendees we have returned to using our committee meeting table this is an effort to make a distinction between this type of meeting and our regular meeting bring us closer and also encourage more discussion between members of council which is difficult to do on a dais when we're all trying to look around each other um so a couple of notes about that um the speakers in front of us will allow us to be heard on the live stream and we've asked our audience to sit in the first two rows so we can be heard in the room um please do speak up but you don't need to yell counselors that's okay um anyone who's making public comment tonight if it's called for can simply stand and do it from their seat and any presenters will be asked to come up to the table this evening and join us so all right and thank you for um uh helping us and bearing with us as we work on this new slash old format for this meeting all right uh counselors the first item tonight is the approval of the may 5th 2025 committee meeting minutes i'll hear a motion on those second we have a motion and a second are there any council comments on the meeting minutes all right hearing none mr harris if you call the role on this one
Mr. Mims. Aye. Mr. Police. Aye. Ms. Graham. Aye. Ms. Stevens. Aye. Mr. Hirsch. Aye. Ms.
Harrison-Vick. Aye. Great. That'll take us to the Committee of the Whole, which we're doing at the head of the meeting tonight. The first item is our Ethics Commission and Applicant Interviews. So we will hold our final interviews for applicants to the Ethics Commission this evening. As a reminder, we heard from our first nominee at our last meeting. applicants were chosen for interviews by rank choice voting system uh thank you to all of you um and originally interviews were held for the top four vote getters but there was a tie so there will be five total we'll have four this evening we will not be voting this evening as a reminder motions to nominate will be heard at our june 10th regular meeting of council and applicants you're not required to attend that meeting but you're of course welcome to um so for our applicants, I'll have you come up and have a seat and join us. I'll ask you to affirm questions that you've already affirmed, but do so for the meeting record. And then you'll have a minute to introduce yourself, talk about why you'd like to serve, and then there'll be time for questions from counsel. And as we did in our last meeting, counselors will just go around and we can ask a question uh or and a follow-up if we'd like of the applicant so uh we'll begin with uh mr paul colbert hello please come on up if you could have a seat right next to councilor diaz there thank you for joining us tonight thank you for being here all right mr colbert i'm going to ask you to affirm those questions uh so first is your primary residence located within the city of of Lancaster? Yes. Thank you. Have you held any appointed or elected office within the city government within the last year? No, I haven't. Have you held any political party office within the last year? No, I haven't. And have you held any political action committee positions within the last year? No, I haven't. Thank you so much. If you would take a minute to please introduce yourself and tell us why you are interested in this commission. Again, my name is Paul Colbreth,
uh lancaster resident lifelong lancaster resident uh born and raised uh graduated mccaskey high school a couple years of college now a couple degrees in college master's in human services and masters of social work uh i spent my first probably 20 years with the boys and girls club of lancaster as the operations director uh then i moved on to uh children and youth and spent the next few several years there as the uh supervisor in the child neglect unit uh at that time i was tapped to take over the urban league of lancaster as the president and ceo uh which i've held that position for about five years before moving on and uh i ended up at daddy stevens college where and i was the director of multicultural affairs student engagement and student retention it's where i retired from i actually retired from there i'm currently the president of the local branch of the national action network which is the social service organization that that targets issues dealing with the quality of life issues here in lancaster city for our community residents thank you so much
shade that um i'm going to just go around to members of council uh for your questions um as a reminder you all submitted some questions so i just aggregated them in a list and you can choose to use them if you wish or you could ask a different one uh councilor diaz we'll just go
right around we'll we'll be in with you how do you see yourself holding accountability to the checks and balance needed for the city and fairness to her residents uh
in many of my positions uh i've held those types of responsibilities uh especially uh in the area with uh issues with the city issues with the college issues with community residents so i have i think a strong background ground in in voting people organizations and entities accountable thank you councillor hirsch thank you paul for
joining us. How do you kind of ensure that your personal beliefs or biases maybe don't affect necessarily a situation where you're called to be an impartial arbiter or mediator? How do you
ensure that... Excuse me, I have artillery ears. No worries. Sorry about that. How do you ensure
that your personal beliefs don't necessarily conflict with your responsibility to be an impartial uh uh arbiter or mediator um how how would i really not understanding your question just asking like how do you make sure that your personal beliefs or biases don't get in the way
of being neutral okay that was sorry that's a little more concise yeah um during my tenure at Thaddeus Stevens, I ran and orchestrated or organized a program where we had to bring a lot of folks in to check out their ability to be biased in some of the decision-making pertaining to the college itself, its programs, its students, and things like that. I myself you know, had to make sure that my biases didn't impact any of my decisions, and I'm pretty comfortable with separating myself from the issue at hand, my biases and feelings and things of that nature to the issue at hand and deal with only the facts. Thank you. Thank you. I'll go.
I'll just help him as we go around. Mr. Colbert, thank you again for being here tonight. This is, of course, a volunteer position. Have you ever served on any other volunteer boards or commissions, and what did you learn from that experience?
I served, I did a stint here in Lancaster on the Human Relations Commission. I think I served probably about one term on there. I think that was during, I would date myself, but it was early. And I was introduced to a lot of the things that will be impacting the city and some of the things that the ethics committee will be dealing with.
Thank you.
Thank you, Mr. Colbert, for being here with us this evening. How do you believe that integrity and honesty and elected officials can build community engagement and trust?
It's paramount to building the trust, especially with the community. If you don't have integrity, you can't really accomplish anything. integrity uh will lead to you know holding the city administration city folks and everybody accountable to uh to the issues at hand or the ethical issues that may be confronted by medicine
thank you madam president um good evening paul thank you for your willingness to serve uh how will you ensure that your decisions are consistent across cases within the commission regardless of the person's political power or connections uh well i think you have to
really be comfortable with uh your ability to understand the issues and to really analyze the issue and then like you said make sure that your your personal opinions and things but also
proactively guide city officials on how to make good decisions that reflect the values of justice diversity transparency and community benefit considering both the intended and unintended impacts of the decisions we make and the desires that our residents have for their communities so that's what really brings me uh here to this table thank you so much i'll do it now
so how do you see yourself holding accountability to checks and balance needed for the city and the
fairness of to the residents good question um i think when it comes to accountability especially through an ethics commission it really comes through transparency and making sure that the ethics commission is transparent in the work it does whether it is reporting at a city council or publishing their findings for the public to see so when it comes to accountability our role as the ethics commission is to review and report it is up to the city and how they would like to um decide to punish and as far up to um charges if need be so that's how that would
thank you councillor hirsch uh thank you grant um i couldn't help but notice uh in reviewing your application your uh and you mentioned your human resources um background and so i I can imagine that you've probably come across a situation where you have handled an ethics complaint. Can you talk about how you approach that and how you'd handle that situation?
Yeah, usually ethics complaints or complaints in general are met with investigatory powers of HR. So often it is interviewing firsthand people who have, you know, are impacted, getting their sides of the story, getting any third party witnesses, and then ultimately coming to a decision, whether it is as a team, HR team, or looking for other players, other city officials to advise on whether good practices were followed, and then ultimately coming up with a decision on what action plan will be put in place for that ethics infraction thank you thank you
can you tell us about any other volunteer positions you've held on boards or commissions what were they and what was something you learned by doing that
yes currently i serve on the personnel committee of the odc or occupational development center of of Lancaster. I've learned a lot from them. I've learned that running a small nonprofit is not easy, and that you really do have to work with the community and build your, your base your resources in order to survive.
This is true. Thank you so much. That's our man.
Thank you for being here. Thank you. How do you believe that integrity and honesty and elected officials can help build trust and engagement in the community
yeah um integrity um i think people like to think of it as you know making the right decision when nobody's looking um and i think that the ethical code of conduct or an ethical framework would help um develop trust uh with the community uh knowing that there is guidelines for decision making in the city that put the community at the center. When integrity is mentioned, I think when we hold our city officials and myself to integrity, I think it comes down to is when nobody's watching across the table inside the committee meetings, are we treating each other with respect, have similar goals towards justice, truth, and ultimately community benefit.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you for being here tonight. How will you ensure that your decisions, your decisions are consistent across cases?
So we can be commission regardless of a person's political power or connections. Oh, yeah, I think it comes from listening. Ultimately, we are a bunch of people with different opinions in a room. If it ever came to the point of needing to recuse myself, I would do that, but listening to different opinions I think is imperative to coming to a consensus. Thank you. Good evening.
Good evening. Could you tell us about a time when you had an ethical dilemma and how you solved it?
Absolutely. So in a former position that I held, I did hold a POA with the IRS, and once that position was done um ethically i had responsibility to end that poa and no longer represent the company so in that regard the ethics dilemma was resolved um i think there's other ethics dilemmas that i've noticed um one that particularly um is recent um one that shows that residents aren't being prioritized in our city and that comes with the residential permit parking program we are in a crisis parking crisis and as the city committed to reviewing our residential permit parking program we might not see any changes until 2026 meanwhile the parking authority has committed to continued ticketing and now continue ticketing via cameras so putting that ethical framework into the lens is it okay to uh what's gone fine before we fix is the same that i put in place so that's kind of like a an example of how an ethical framework would guide
decision making here and now thank you thank you very much counselors any additional questions thank you thank you for joining us thank you thank you and last but not least we have christopher solt this is where you're the first one here and you're the last one but i was going alphabetically so i apologize for that okay i'm going to have you affirm these questions uh is your primary residence within the city of leicester yes uh have you held any appointed or elected office within the city government within the last year have you held any political party office within the last year have you held any political action committee position within the last year i have not it's I'm going to give you a minute to introduce yourself and talk about why you'd like to serve.
Mayor, Madam President, Council Members, I'm really honored to be here and also really enjoyed hearing the interviews of the other candidates. My name is Chris Solt. I was born and raised in Vermont. I actually grew up in Burlington, Vermont, which I'll get back to next very quickly. Then I moved to Cleveland, Ohio, and I lived in the inner city there for about 27 years. And then my wife and I moved here in 2018. And we love it here. We're never moving. Love this place dearly. I worked for an organization called 10,000 Villages, which is just 20 minutes north of here, starting in 2006. And I traveled to the city often. And so I got to know the city for about 20, last 20 years and fell in love with it. So I kind of feel like this is kind of my kind of new adopted home. Yeah, so I've worked in the fair trade world for about 20 years and I saw somebody sent me this opportunity and I was like, oh, I see a lot of what I've devoted my career to in this position. I think that what you all do in public service is I think a very special kind of calling and also has a special responsibility, which I think is something that should be shared with the community. So I think that's really interesting new opportunity for the city to help, I'd say, be a better
city. Thank you so much.
Okay. Councilor Diaz. Thank you for coming. How do you see yourself holding accountability to the checks and balance needed for the city and fairness to our residents?
Yeah. Well, as you could probably tell, like being in the fair trade world, the fairness is something that is something is very passionate i'm very passionate about um and uh kind of interestingly in my organization now we have a code of practice that we hold 200 uh small businesses to the united states and canada they've agreed to behave a certain way and they've asked us to hold them accountable so i'm very familiar with that kind of dance right it's a very important one to make I think that within a group having lots of diverse opinions, that's all very great, and building community within that group is important, but to understand the letter of the law, right, and the rule of law that we have agreed to work with, right? So I think being very mindful and building a lot of understanding with what are the tools that we are actually using to work, rather than, like, my own personal opinion about a policy or something that impacts me as a resident, I think continuously grounding ourselves in the basis of the ethics act, which is passed by the, you know, Pennsylvania legislature.
Councilor Hirsch.
Thank you, Chris, for being here. I was going to ask how your personal beliefs, how do you avoid them interfering with your decision making? You kind of just spoke to that. So I'll ask, you know, how would you handle a situation where you know someone was the subject of an ethics complaint?
If I knew them?
Yes, if they were a colleague, if they were someone you worked with.
Yeah, obviously, it depends on certainly the context and situation, of course. But for the sake of this question, I'd say once we understood the context of that situation, then, you know, first, I would probably want to recuse myself. If that was, you know, I would automatically offer that if that would help the situation come to some better resolution. Being able to understand the the hat that you wear, per se, is really important in any kind of ethics work that you would do. And knowing that if my presence as an individual would then undermine the successful outcome of that is very, very important to understand. um it's it's challenging obviously and kind of messy but i think that my my first inclination would be to you know if i like knew somebody and they were part of it that i would recuse myself
thank you can you tell us about any uh volunteer boards or commissions you've served on in the past what were they and what did you learn from that experience yeah um so i've served on when i lived
in cleveland i was part of a little um housing cooperative and i was the vice president and treasurer of that organization for about seven years. I was several positions on the Hesler Neighborhood Association Historic Preservation Community Development Organization in Cleveland. That was probably about 10 years. And I'm currently the vice president of the World Fair Trade Organization. In my second term, I was elected in September of 2019 in Lima, Peru by this global group of fair trade enterprises around the world. I served one term, which was extended. It four-year term was extended five years to one year excuse me two five years from four years because of the pandemic and then was just re-elected last september in cape town south africa to another term and with them was internally elected to be the vice president that's all volunteer um and also i've worked uh my 10 years with 10 000 villages i did a lot of non-profit board development as well across the united states and in canada and um yeah so there's a couple others but that's kind of the bulk of it thank you so much for sharing that councilman thank you
council president thank you for being here this evening how do you believe that integrity and honesty and elected officials can build trust and engagement in the community yeah but um someone
else just mentioned our current um political dialogue and um you know the tone right now is is really stark i think that in lancaster city um especially we have an opportunity to control what we have going in our community the integrity and trust that you all have and and lancaster elected officials have with residents is the currency by which you are able to spend the trust of the residents and the you know that you're supposed to represent their interests and if that's you know if that's seen as somehow damaged or somehow tainted in some way then it doesn't allow you to fully represent all the residents in the city to make the best community possible
i mean it's really the biggest issue right thank you council clicks thank you council president thank you for being here tonight and uh how will you ensure that your decisions are consistently worst cases within the commission regardless of a person's political power or connections
yeah it's such a great question and it's also a very very difficult one to ensure but is the right question to be asking um i think certainly from my own individual standpoint um being very very mindful about my own presentation of my own power and privilege and white male you know old i've got gray beard here you know english speaking u.s password i have a whole list of things that have some type of power and privilege associated with them and being mindful about what that represents to people is really important also all of the individuals um within you know the ethics commission would also be very very important to understand as well and then in all of the individuals involved in a specific case are also really important to understand then you know we can have our own opinions we can have our own thoughts we're all human but like the code is the code right so like that is what we we go by we can discuss all of our opinion opinions about things and the way we feel or emotions or whatever we're humans that's relevant in that conversation but any action needs to be cited by right by the um ethics act right so there's it's important to to vent and have those discussions and community and collaboration um and also making sure that everyone no matter their power and privilege has a way to be heard and listened and suspected but the law's law right so that i think is is what will drive everything
thank you thank you that's okay hello hello could you tell us about a client when you had enough of a dilemma and i'm sorry oh my goodness i have so many and that i could share publicly
um yeah so yeah i've i've been in hr and training for a long time so i have lots of of examples where there were was a complaint an ethics complaint and then there was another a reaction to someone who was a part of that and oftentimes you know those conflicts which have a lot of experience unfortunately with conflict management um that you know usually those are misunderstandings so like being able to listen to people and have them be heard and respected and then bring them together to them understand there's some issue here right but there's also some misunderstanding trying to build understanding um i'm generalizing because i don't want to go into specific examples but that that's usually how i approach those one example that i can share is um actually just in um so i'm the executive director of the fair trade federation and we have like i said 200 businesses in the united states and canada if you're at all familiar with the fair trade movement it comes from a great place right so wanting to do good to represent marginalized producers and farmers around the world the way i was introduced to it was sally struthers and it was so othering this experience where it was like this white saviorism you know you give you know a dollar a day this person starving little kid in ethiopia can be have a slightly better life and that whole kind of like culture and language othering white saviorism and and um heropreneurship as i like to call it has been kind of the heart of that that's the kind of values pitch and it's not right right so like i kept pointing this out to the organization for many years like and finally got to a place where i was like okay we need to do something about this and like decolonize the language that we're using right so it doesn't other those people we're saying one thing and we we we're telling this emotional story but what we're doing actually as harm to other people so when i said okay um i'm the like old white guy in the room i don't think this is right but we need to do something about this and um i probably am not the person to be the face of this conversation so i recused myself from that full conversation and created a space for people who were really passionate about the issue and they talked about it and came up with uh we came up with a jedi commission justice secretary diversity inclusion and they were given a charge so to go through and decolonize a lot of our language we kind of it's a slow thing because it's a big you know kind of cultural change so that was one thing where i i feel like i used my power and privilege to kind of create a space for others um where i saw like back to what i was saying earlier me being in that conversation probably wouldn't be the best i mean i would be there if it was needed but there's the optics of it as well um so that was that was one thing it was i know it's a complicated ethical thing but to me that was something where i felt like i needed to step away but help create the space for that conversation thank you thank you counselors any
additional questions okay so thank you so much thank you appreciate it for all of our applicants thank you again again we will hear motions for appointment on our next meeting at june 10th there'll be a place on the agenda for it as a reminder we are charged with appointing three members to the ethics commission so just keep that in mind and we will hear more at our next meeting you're welcome to stay or you can go that's okay thank you very much we will continue with committee of the whole our next item is the administrative code introduction uh barry hamburger city solicitor is here this evening to talk us through that and mr hamburger do you have
a presentation i do okay does mr harris have that he does okay great well that's getting going those are great interviews all five of them so we'll have a very difficult decision difficult choice
And it's an intimidating, I mean, there's six of us on the one, so it's kind of a lot. And it's a brand new thing, so.
All right. Please.
Well, following up on home rule topics, since you're dealing with the Ethics Commission, which is something created by the Home Rule Study Commission and the adopted charter, you also have an obligation under the charter and the home rule law to adopt an administrative code. And we have meetings scheduled later to start introducing sections of the code to you for consideration and for your beginning to have discussions and guidance towards those ends. In order to help frame that for you, I thought it would be helpful to have a presentation to go a little bit over the law that relates to it, the process that the law requires, the process that your study commission went through to frame what you're going to see ultimately and what you're ultimately going to have to adopt. So as a little bit of history and reminder, this council, by ordinance, formed a government study commission to study the form of government in the city of Lancaster. That study commission determined to move from a third-class city under the optional charter law to a home rule study, to a home rule municipality, and crafted and proposed a charter. That charter was submitted to the electors of the City of Lancaster in November of 2024 and was adopted. It became effective on January 1st, 2025. The charter and the Home Rule Charter and Optional Plans Law require that council by ordinance, and I want you to keep that in mind, it's by ordinance. There's a significant feature to this. By ordinance, adopt an administrative code, Mr. Harris. so understanding a little bit about what home rule does in terms of city governance is very relevant to the administrative code as a third class city prior to adopting a home rule charter the city could only do what it was specifically authorized by statute or law to do no power to do anything that wasn't directed by the state legislature. Home rule transfers the authority to make those decisions to you, to the city, to city council and the city. Essentially, with home rule, you can now do anything that state or federal law does not prohibit. It's a big difference. So if you were to take a look at some of the operational codes in the past, the third class city code and the third class optional federal law being the primary ones, Mr. Harris, you can slip to the next slide. They were in large part pieces of legislation that set forth the authority to do things for the city. And absent that authority or absent some other law that granted you authority, you couldn't do anything. They also set forth procedures by which you would have to do certain of those, exercise certain of those powers. So not only did the third class city code give you the authority, but it set forth procedures that you were required to follow in order to exercise them that were dictated by the state legislature. You do not have to put in the code your powers. The powers, as we said, are going to be determined by the existence of existing law. What you do have to do is draft an administrative code that sets forth the procedures you'll follow in exercising whatever power you choose to exercise. The administrative code is adopted by ordinance, and therefore it can be amended by ordinance. This is indeed the most legislative flexibility a municipality in Pennsylvania can have. It's very free-flowing. How long does it take you to adopt an ordinance? You can do it. Two meetings, generally, right? So whatever you adopt here, you get to change. If you want, if times change, if the law changes, if your operations change. And this is the single biggest change from the way we've operated for decades, which is everything had to be specifically set forth by a state statute. It puts the most level of self-governance that a Pennsylvania municipality can have into your hands. So we move to the next slide where we talk a little bit about what the administrative code is mandated, what you're mandated to have. um the things that are going to be in your administrative code are mandated from two different sources and really three but the two the two mandate sources are there some things that the home rule and home rule optional plans law requires and there there's some things that your charter which your electors your your voters elected and adopted require you to include in the administrative code five general categories provisions for the exercise of a control function for the management of finances enumeration of the department's offices authorities boards commissions and other administrative units of the city government their scope of responsibility and internal procedures for operation budgeting accounting and financial policies purchasing and acquisition procedures policies and procedures governing personnel policies position descriptions employee recruitment selection orientation training benefits promotion and discharge Other topics will be in the administrative code that weren't mandated by the law, include things, for example, regarding forfeiture of office. So there's a provision in your charter that mandates that city council set forth the procedure to be followed in order for an elected official to have forfeited their office, be deemed a forfeiter. There's other similar things throughout that will be throughout. in attempting to come to a give you guys a starting point because this will be your code we've taken a few items and sort of concepts and kept them in mind as we are drafted the first is next slide yeah and you can select your next library sorry the first is to be consistent with the terms and spirit of the charter that's obviously the most significant right the charter is now your Bible. That is the law of the land. It is the single biggest law underneath the Pennsylvania Constitution. That's what your electors have said is the law. Any court's going to interpret any ambiguity as against the charter. So we obviously need to make sure that you are consistent with not only the specific language, but the spirit. Assure internal controls and checks and balances. This is to protect the taxpayers. Continue current practices where appropriate to assure that change is made only where needed or desired. Assure best practices. Obviously, the city wants to be the best it can be, and be directive only where necessary and prudent. This is to maintain your flexibility. I take these principles, and I kind of summarize them in one phrase, which is sound governance. I mean, if you think about these five, these are principles that your administrative code should set forth that assure that the city is administered and governed in a sound manner next slide so what will the new code look like what's on the screen is the table of contents from your current on the left hand side from your current codified ordinances under the home rule charter law our charter has to be the various very first item in the code it's already been placed there because member became effective january 1st the administrative code doesn't have to repeat and really shouldn't repeat all of the things in your 62-page chart your electors have already determined many of the procedures that you're mandated to follow and set them out very clearly we have in our current code of ordinances a next section entitled administrative legislation of which there are a multitude of items Many of these will either be merged into your administrative code, moved out of this section because they're really more general legislation than they are administrative code, and or modified in terms of new language based on the flexibility that you've now been given in terms of self-governance and, quite frankly, updated. So a lot of these have been in place decades and decades, and this is a good opportunity to even where there's no real substantive change needed. Some of these have references that are outdated, and so they will all be tweaked and cleaned up and incorporated into this part of it. What's below general legislation. So this is where your your your your big legislative ordinances lie. right? So your zoning ordinance, your subdivision and land development ordinance, your building codes ordinance, your property maintenance ordinance, your stormwater ordinance, your sewer ordinance, your water ordinance, your streets ordinance, all of the big ordinances that we think of, they're not getting touched. They're still the law and they will continue to be the law unless changed by ordinance of city council. The only thing that's getting worked on is the administrative portions. And that's what the administrative code is meant to cover. uh next slide so the next several slides are and you notice the word draft because you ultimately have to craft the administrative code and what we've been working on is to give you the starting point um based on and i'll just be honest based on you know me being around the city since 1994 my experience both in-house uh here in the last five years and while serving as outside counsel for the city of Lancaster, an understanding of the law and an understanding of the things that we think should be in here. In many cases, you're not changing anything that you're doing now. So in some cases, we're making what is actually in writing conform to what we do now, which is always sometimes moved and changed without change in ordinance and legislation. But as we walk through, you'll see, I mean, obviously short title and definition. When you see something here like powers and division of powers, organizational structure, department of officials, those are all things that are already covered in your charter. This will not be a repeat of the information. These are where the study commission left places for you as counsel to set forth procedure and weigh in on how things will be done. So these are the broad categories, but it's not a repeat of what's in the charter. So you can see here organizational structure. remember, I mentioned earlier, we have to lay out all the departments and the organizational that's mandated by the option by the home rule charter law to be in the charter, even though we have it in other places, we need to put it in here. And so that is one place where there is a little bit of a rinse and repeat from the charter. But that's because the law requires us to do so. You'll see salaries of elected officials is is in your charter. But what's left out of the charter and on purpose from the study commission was when and when you make the changes? Are there any restrictions on making the changes and how? So that's what's going to be expanded upon by you folks in the draft of your administrative code. This section here, Article 5, requirements of elected officials regarding confidential information, and another section that has a similar title but covers a broader sector of employees as well. This is starting to be where your ethics code might be part of it. It could be standalone. It might be inserted in these provisions. These titles are placeholders for me and the mayor in order to express places where some of this language may appear. Next slide, please. So again, if you recall your administrative ordinances section of your current code, a lot of these topics that you see under city council are already being repeated. The reason being is, again, we're going to take that set of language that's already there and we're going to bring it current to your current practices. there are some things that need to be mandated in the code by the charter so for example the charter mandates that you meet twice a month right so there are things that have to be brought current as we do this again article 7 ordinances and resolutions again there's things left blank or unsaid in terms of some of the specific procedures in terms of ordinances and resolutions in the administrative code you have provisions for that now and a lot of those are going to be merged right into here. I mentioned earlier, there's a new provision required by the charter regarding forfeiture of offices, of office of elected officials. So this is a section you will not have seen or even had any sight to see anywhere before. And you can slip to the next slide, Berner, please. So when we get to boards, commissions, and authorities, again, there's some new methodologies and requirements in the charter for how members are appointed. This is laying out a little bit more detail. It will also do something that's necessary, which is to confirm that current board members' terms will continue. One of the sort of oddities of the law is by adopting a new charter. We've already done it with your charter, but we need to do it again with the administrative code. There'll be things like training. Trainings are covered in here, which is not something that currently exists, but something that we're proposing and you already
have in practice so again being merged into the code itself rather than as a resolution which is
what we currently have article 10 conflicts of interest and disclosure of confidential information again this is starting to get into some things that might be in the ethics code these are sort of starting places and holding places for that we do need to have a section on budgets so that's what article 11 covers and what we've done here what we're proposing to do here is you have very detailed budget sections of your charter but what we're doing here is is again expanding on it we're bringing the calendars into the administrative code making them a little bit more less wordy and more tabular so they're followable um again so this is for transparency too right so anybody looking at our code should be able to understand when the budgets are going to be presented in the process hopefully this will this is a starting point for you to discuss how to do that we need to have a section on finance uh and accounting and that's article 12 or at least the proposed article 12 and you know we have to have the city to have the ability to have bank accounts so this and these are all things in your charter uh you can slip the slide switch slides better um but the types of things up here are things that we all do but we don't think about the procedure they're all authorized by the charter but now we're setting forth the procedure so how do we you know what sort of fund policy should we have what sort of investment policy should we have what sort of borrowing policies should we have? How do we process transactions? All those were things covered in some part and sometimes not by the third class city code. Obviously, Article 13, procurement and disposal of city property. Insurance and bonding is dealing with several significant insurance issues, which we just want to make sure are covered. A new article here is records and record retention, which is an article intended to make sure that we're compliant with the state record retention law, which I know is an issue that's been before this council in the recent months. Next slide, please. Article 16 will have a whole lot more sections than one and two. The main reason is that employment guidelines is going to be broken down into a whole lot of subcategories. That whole long list that I spoke about earlier would be included in there. Keep in mind that the administrative code does not need to lay out every procedure. It needs to lay out how procedures will be created as well so there there will be things here that are directing how policies are are enacted and and if they're enacted and they affect for example the citizens and residents how do people know about um so when you get to the general provisions which skipping civil service for a second you'll see uh publicly accessible websites so there's some going to be some requirements that we're we're suggesting be built in here about what has to be on that website how it's used how it's maintained to assure that residents and taxpayers and others that are interested have good clear and up-to-date information regarding city affairs obviously article 17 civil service that is a law that predates many of the laws and is mandated on us so the civil service provisions which we already have in our existing codes what we brought here into article 17. uh next slide so how we how we have uh how this is starting for you this is just the start but um four four meetings work sessions of the committee of the whole have been scheduled um one a couple weeks from now uh one in july one in august one in september the plan if i can meet all the drafting needs is to to present about half of this on june 17th and work through that on the 17th and the 15th with still ability obviously to carry on with more discussions um and then present the second half for discussion on august 19th for subject first for discussion on august 19th and september 16th one of the key components to this obviously is what happens with your ethics code which you're ultimately responsible for drafting but you can't draft it without input from the ethics commission so this this schedule is in large part um determined uh controlled to some extent by uh how fast we can get your ethics commission up and running and giving you the guidance it needs
to draft that first version of an ethics code which is why it will be on the second phase of the work not what's presented obviously on june 17th um next slide bernard so next steps um
council action well you've already got one you're starting with which is completion of the ethics commission appointments um review a draft of the administrative code and complete transition um really to complete the transition from third-class cities to home rule is to adopt this administrative code ordinance one thing that's not on here and i i'll say it i think it's probably um logical but i really do think before the meeting on the 17th i would i would highly recommend that council members spend a good deal of time really looking at the charter and reading its language repeatedly really digging into it because it's what's going to control this and if you don't have a good understanding of what's in the charter it's going to make this a harder process for you by understanding the charter really well you'll see immediately when these come to you where we've where we we are expanding on what the charter told asked us to expand on and where the sort of the impetus is coming from your questions and guidance are vitally important throughout this process this will be your code it is the city's code it is every city council's code and the beautiful thing about it is it can be changed as environment in this in the in the country changes as law changes as the city adapts as you adapt from a just a personal note you know I started practicing with the city in 1994 to actually be part of this and have the opportunity to hand this to you and let you do what you need to do with it is a real big honor for me. It's something that is a living, breathing document that I take extremely seriously about the provisions of sound governance coming through it. The city has fortunately, in my opinion, been soundly governed for many, many years, but the third-class city codes have restricted it from creative thinking, creative decision-making. This is going to require council members to maintain sound governance and marry that against critical and unique thinking and not subvert the process for, well, we just want to do something that no one's ever done before and the law doesn't allow. This document is to guide you to make sure that you're thinking through everything you need to think over time. And so I look forward to meeting with you each of those four meetings, to getting questions from you in the public. I know we'll talk about a way to submit questions so that we can get revised answers and drafts and research throughout the process because it's going to be a lot. I'll tell you that we're not done drafting and we're at about the same length as the charter in small font, 11 point font, not the same size font as what's in the charter, so there's quite a bit there, but again, a lot of it shouldn't be real new. I mean, there's a good portion of it that's really not. We will try to present information in a way that you can understand where it's coming from, where it's been changed, where something's new, and hopefully this will be a process that we can get done here over the next several months. Can I, really quick,
can I, I want to kind of go back to the idea of the work session and how those meetings will go, because this is going to be very different than even a committee meeting like we're sitting here, although this is kind of my first step in hoping to bring us together on those. These work sessions will really be similar to the Home Rule Study Commission's work in that we will be having discussion, there will be time for questions, but there's no action that's going to be taken, the votes that are going to be taken at these meetings. So, Barry, you said, you know, make come prepared know the charter really really well because everyone will be asked to weigh in on these things and and and kind of bring your perspective um and some of it could be super easy and and it makes sense to just simply carry things forward but there will be things we'll need to make some decisions about but there's no voting when we make those decisions because what we're doing is putting it all together into one administrative code that will be uh have a first reading to adopt it on October 28th on that schedule before us, and then a second reading and a vote on November 11th. So the work sessions are truly just that. They are places for council to have discussion. So my hope is that everyone will come really prepared to do so, and it is, like I said, very different than a regular meeting as well. So just be prepared for that. And if I could
just add to that thank you council president um you're not going to have days to review the first tranche of this we're going to send it out to council and make it public and barry's going to do a walkthrough of the content and show you the sections that are reflect major changes and sections that are the continuation of the way that we have been doing things all of it is up for grabs but we are we're going to try to focus on the things that are of significant change council will then have some several weeks two weeks or so two and a half weeks to then submit written questions as will the public those written questions will be funneled to the solicitor's office then he will work on responding and doing research and whatever else that is necessary to respond to the inquiries draft alternative language for the consideration of this body and then at the second meeting uh july 15th we'll review all the questions and comments from council and the public for that section have further discussion and then where there's consensus great and where there is still not consensus and we may need to come back to that that particular topic we will figure out a time frame for doing that but we kept this so that by the middle of September we kind of have given you all have given the administration marching orders in terms of like what where you want to see final language then with a sufficient enough time before the end of October to actually see a revised and somewhat final draft before adoption in in potentially in November so I just want to explain the cadence of the meetings because they are going to be different um but you will have like the homework for now is just read the charter the next batch of homework is to read the draft and provide comment um ask questions for clarity things like that then discussion and then we repeat that whole process for the second tranche of uh content um so and i think we we've done our best to try to split the content it's not all going to flow like one article after the other because some things are still in draft form you know some things we still need like the ethics um ethics code um but that but we're we're trying to like give you the things that and a little bit of a balance of like this is relatively easy this is a little bit more complicated rather than putting like all the hard stuff into one bucket we're trying to navigate that so that there's a cadence where we can kind of like the flywheel can start moving because it is a lot but it's not a lot that's changing but there are certain sections of course that are new and that things are that are being added to change and we hope
that consensus will be easy on a lot of them and to put some humor into it so for example if you remember one of the various first topics was short title like normally this would be called administrative code or city of lancaster administrative code or administrative code of the city of lancaster we would hope that like we can get consensus on one of those fairly quickly and easily right now there are going to be other things that clearly require your input and that you're going to have different opinions on and again what we're attempting to do is give you a starting point this is not hey you have to do this because this is counselors that's a and b um there are lots of reasons that some of these things may be changed or not changed so it's it really is a starting point um it's going to be the most significant in terms of length piece of legislation this council has done uh during the mayor's term um and i can't think of one longer in my time here um and in some ways a lot of it is minutia but a lot of the minutia is really important so um that's why that's why you know we ended this with you know your your questions your guidance is vitally important
and counselors i think the biggest one of the biggest takeaways besides read the charter and get ready for this is that and nothing that we're doing is written on a stone tablet just like today we change pieces of our existing administrative code often by ordinance or resolution so we can change these pieces um but we need to get one in place we have a ticking clock in front of us and it's good work to dive into but it's not um not something that can be never
changed again nothing here is ever written in stone the only thing that's really written in stone is that you can't make any significant changes to the structure of government right within five years without doing another going through the same process we just went through correct that's that's written in stone right that's um uh what's in the charter is written in stone but everything else is is written in pencil okay thank you so much anything else that
on that topic counselors anything to add i have a question if i may for those that don't read english will there be translations for this group here no for anything that's going to be well i
mean i i'd have to ask the mayor whether the staff will be able to translate drafts as they're moving
on candidates yeah let me get back to you about that because um we are we we try very hard when we're doing uh official business like this to have a professional translator translate the the concept like the concepts of government which can sometimes not get translated well in like a google for example um but i'm not sure that we're going to have the staff capacity or the financial resources um in our budget now to translate iterations of this but translating at the end um yeah so let's talk about it because i think that that's going to be a challenge for us on the timeline that we have to translate each section in-house there is software though that can automatically translate yeah it's just what we found with that counselor diaz not google yeah some of it is not it some of it is not translated as well as we would like if someone were actually you know um walking through it and talking about how to explain this particular concept in a
different language this just in case anybody comes forward and says why hasn't this been translated i will just direct them to you because you would be the one that would be responsible answering and being transparent to them because i'm sure it will come up yeah and and obviously we would
be happy to if there are specific sections that people are particularly interested in we we can certainly work to address those particular areas but as it relates to a 100 page document that's going to continue to be revised multiple times and i just don't know that i know that we do not have the budget line item for translation that would support that thank you
anything additional from council yeah thank you kelts president my only question comment i guess would be more of a comment is uh you know other than reading and getting more familiar with the charter how could we make sure that this body stays on pace with these meetings and not try to rewrite the charter in a working session well i guess that's going to be hopefully
uh some guidance from me um and being able to point you to where the charter already controls something um and then just to focus as a group on um where the goal line is right so like we may have to you may have to make some concessions to the shortness of time at various points where like okay we've deliberated this for an hour on the point of the name of the code um i think we need to move forward um and i think i think i think as a group you guys will be able to do that um i'm um i'm and in terms of the timing i'm more concerned ultimately just with um the ethics part of it and that has a that has an absolute 12-month deadline um and for me getting them done together makes the most sense trying to do the admin code after the ethics code um is is challenging even though legally we have six months longer for this um that being said that to me is the biggest challenge to the time frame is ethics code's got to get appointed uh and then we need to get them convened with a meeting to give some feedback um and ideas and that's going to take more than one meeting i mean they're not going to be able to come up in one meeting the study commission fortunately did a whole lot of work on ethics commissions and we have a whole lot of information assembled by the study commission um pennsylvania economy league that uh was guiding them that we can give to the ethics commission to get them started to give us the feedback necessary to get started on an amend code on an ethics code provision that you ultimately are still responsible for their job is to give you preliminary input your job is to draft and adopt and i would i mean
this is also for your discussion as a working group i mean if you guys want to create a little bit of uh you know um how you want to work together you know that you uh you check in after 15 minutes of discussion and decide you know like is there consensus around this do we need to move on you know that there are some kind of agreed upon ways that you want to carry this out um that you that basically if they're if it's presented and you know um mr handwerker is like okay does anybody have any significant concerns and if there aren't okay we're moving on just those that kind of pace and then where there are concerns and you know it's only one person that has concerns then that person gets heard and then if there's any other additional conversation about it if not then you know we do have to go with consensus but also everyone should be heard so you all can decide how you want to do that i would also say i would encourage you to use
the month in between each meeting to you know independently send questions over i mean obviously you can't deliberate by emails in between but you can send questions to me um that i can and you have a question why did you do this or why does it say that why doesn't it say this those are the types of things that we can certainly work to answer to keep maybe the the work sessions moving a little more uh fluidly because some of those preliminary questions will have already been
answered and i will say maybe even if we could um have some uh education to the public on the process and the timeline and if they could also ask questions in between directly to the administration so the meetings aren't getting bogged down with you know a question and answer
session um yeah i will i will say that the work sessions because they're not legislative won't have general public comment the questions and answers that we are submitting can also be submitted there will be general comments i'm sorry specific comment is really what i'm saying general comment yes similar to the home rule study commission meetings but for each individual item that we're working on no um so they will be able to use that and there is going to be communication yeah looking at the public talked about this a little bit and preparing uh to the public about what these sessions are how they will function and how they can ask questions and you know the the drafts will be available to them the same time that they're available to us so yeah and so i
think just for those of you just related home rule on the point of public comment the work sessions happened there was dialogue among all the home rule commissioners and then at the end they took public comment and the public could comment on any aspect of anything that was discussed or or even not discussed as part of the the charter but there there's not it doesn't require each individual section to pause for public comment it's one public comment that was what i was mainly and the other thing is passed by ordinance as a whole you will be able to say if you have a question
instead of asking the question during the public comment session submit your question if you have a comment we have comments so that you can sort of keep the public sessions to opinions comments
suggestions question and answer can be through the process and the point of of having that gap in between the meetings is to have time to gather the their answers to the questions find the resources that we're looking for um and have them for the next meeting so that we can answer questions everybody's questions um with some authority and not make a guess right and keep
in mind that you know i i don't like to sort of like say i need the time but in reality you're doing a lot of new things and you're under a new structure of government um and you may have a question that i literally don't have the answer to i will have to research and research doesn't happen in a day we can take some time to make sure we give you the right answers or the public the right answers uh so that you're getting the right guidance uh throughout the process and a two-week
period to submit those questions also so that the public and members of council have time to
formulate those questions and right yeah great anything else i'm just gonna ask real briefly um is there any anything we've seen from other cities that have undergone this process that we should take note of either things that have gone well things have not gone well
well uh in in reality no um because we're the most recent city to do it in quite a while the other municipalities that have converted to the home rule one have been different types of municipalities have oftentimes come out of act 47 and had different financial constraints and or different issues. I will tell you that I've looked at other administrative codes. I've tried to pick the parts that were done well. I've relied on guidance from Pennsylvania Economy League to point out where they thought admin codes were particularly well done or particularly not. But is there any one model? No. And the answer reason is because our charter is unique. It's a charter unto ourselves. It's not the charter of Allentown. It's not the charter of, you know, a particular borough, Mahanoy City, for example. While all of those may have some nice language and concepts, they're not yours.
They're always different. I try, because I have a friend that she's a city council person in Minnesota, and we talk back and forth about the charter, and she goes, oh, my God, your charter is really crazy, and she would give me her feedback. So they're all different.
The only way, for instance, that we would have to draft the Administrative Code is Home Rule. Yes. So, to what extent the Administrative Code must comply with state law?
Well, it has to comply with the Home Rule Charter Law. It has to comply with our charter, with those five enumerated topics that must be covered. It can't be inconsistent with the charter. So you can't say, oh, for example, the best, easiest example would be the charter says you must meet twice a month. Well, we want to take, you know, only do like we've been doing and have one meeting in July and August each. You can't do that. You can't write a code that does that. You have to have a code that's consistent with the charter. The charter is your enabling authority. I mean, to state law. again the charter the charter now as a home rule municipality you can do anything that's not prohibited by state law okay so there isn't any state law that's going to say this has to be in your charter other than the five things that five topical areas that i covered earlier and a few topics that are specifically set forth in the charter okay it's why this is a really challenging process uh is to try and figure out a what do we want to do b how should we do it and then c how should we write it um and fortunately you know um the third class city code in many cases is a well-written document not all state legislation is and parts of it i might quibble with but in general it has we've been operating in certain ways because of it and some of those things are incorporated here and because they are best practices. And then there are areas where the charter adopted essentially third-class city code practices. So again, we have some guidance in the form of a third-class city code, but we're not limited by it to the extent that it doesn't conflict with the charter itself. Thank you. You're welcome. Anything else? I thank you very
much for giving us that introduction. Thank you, Counselor. I look forward to diving in. I look forward to seeing you again in June thank you all right so we'll continue with the Committee of the Whole this begins resolutions that will need to be introduced or moved out of committee if Council wishes them to be we begin with council resolution 41 that's recognizing immigrant heritage month and world refugee day uh councilor mend you're introducing this one you'd like to share a little bit about it
uh yes um thank you council president um this is an annual resolution to recognize world refugee day of an immigrant heritage month which is june of 2025 and world refugee day is on june 20th and this resolution is just going to honor and recognize the contributions made by both our immigrant community as well as celebrating world refugee day here in lexington and that concludes
my report great thank you so much for doing that um and counselor med uh do you have a motion on
this one i will move council resolution number 41 2025 to our next meeting of full council on the 10
second motion and a second any council comments on the resolution oh i'm so sorry oh this is committee the whole sorry i'm we're doing it first so we're all backwards um okay uh all those in favor of moving that to our next meeting any opposed thank you very much um our next resolution number 42 is recognizing juneteenth counselor craig you are introducing this one if you have
anything to share with us um not particularly um juneteenth is a relatively new holiday for most people but um in the african-american community it has been recognized for a very long time and um i'm just pleased that the city of lancaster has has um taken it upon themselves to recognize juneteenth and and the history behind it thank you very much and do you have a motion for this one council sure do motion to approve motion to move to full
council on the 10th second any additional council comments on it all in favor any opposed okay thank you so much uh next resolution is resolution number 43 recognizing pride month i am glad to be introducing this one again this year um so it's important i think uh now more than ever that we recognized the celebration of pride month um i also appreciate that june has many different celebrations and uh it you know all have uh equal time and can be celebrated together and i think that that's truly in the spirit of celebrating pride as well um particularly in a year when our uh trans neighbors are also uh very much in danger it's important that we come out and support this community with this resolution so um i would make a motion that we move resolution number 43 to our next meeting with council on june 10th second motion in a second are there any council comments on the resolution hearing none all in favor aye any opposed thank you so much the next item under the committee of the whole is administration resolution number 44 this is authorizing flag raising to mark black history month in 2026 so i always appreciate when people get out ahead of these things we do are required to to approve these flag raisings. And this was submitted by the NAACP Lancaster branch for Juneteenth flag raising. And it was submitted, oh, that was last time. Okay, and so, I don't know if I have the date. I apologize, let me just click on that. The old submission that we changed. And this is submitted to take place on February 2nd, 2026 With the backup date of February 3rd, 2026, I would make a motion that we move this resolution to full Council on June 10th. So, the motion and a 2nd counselors, any comments on this 1. Hearing none all in favor any opposed. Thank you very much and. related sort of uh administration resolution number 45 authorizing a flag raising at city hall to mark juneteenth in 2026 again getting out ahead of that uh to be prepared for next year and i'm just bringing that up to ensure that i have the right dates and this was also submitted by the naacp lancaster branch and they're requesting to do the flag raising on june 19th 2026 with a backup date of the 18th in case uh was calling for inclement weather that day i would make a motion that we move this resolution to full council on the 10th second second with a motion and a second counselors any comments on the resolution here none all those in favor any opposed thank you uh and that will conclude the committee of the whole thank you everybody um we'll now begin the personnel committee uh counselor clicks do you have the floor thank you council president
so the personal committee has four items on the agenda for tonight and that the first item is elimination of molly's uh new order bone trigger for appointment to the shade tree commission would you please join us thank you for being here tonight and thank you for your willingness to serve would you please introduce yourself starting with your name and block of residence and tell us
why you want to serve on the shade tree commission okay my name is marlisa yoder bontrager i live on i first moved to south hand street in 1988 so i've been there for a long long time and i've been involved with tree planting in that area just about since 1988 um and it's been neighborhood tree planting it's been also in the northeast um and um yeah i just i value trees really highly wherever they are but i think in an urban environment especially with the city's goals for water storm water reduction general life quality cooling all those things i think they're just a really valuable asset and i'd like to do more to support the city in getting more trees in the ground keeping the ones that we have healthy thank you
are there any questions from other members of the committee comments uh thank you marlisa for
stepping forward i know you bring a lot of background like you said to this issue are
there things that you feel like as far as what the city is doing and getting us both the street trees and shade trees but also just its overall tree canopy things of the city should do better or what maybe things that are that are going well yeah I
think that we could do change the traditional approach of just putting a single sidewalk street tree in to doing planting strips to doing cluster planting in areas where we're off the sidewalk a little bit uh and in that way create more habitat and more storm water reduction um i think that there could be more coordination probably between departments i um i don't know a lot of the background but it seems to me like sometimes sidewalks are uh put in without maybe consultation with the from the from the tree perspective from the um city arborist and the urban the urban what are you called mike forester forester um so i would like to see a very tight connection between when work is being done and um always keeping in mind what the opportunities might be for adding tree trees to whatever
location thank you uh are there any other questions or comments from members of the
committee from council and the whole council thank you marley so thank you for being here i just wanted to make mention are you a nurse also thank you i appreciate that and thank you for being doing that what you do and then also being interested in chantries i just think that's
neat it's kind of lifelong yeah thank you thank you so now i'll make a motion to move uh this nomination to our next council meeting on june 10th second all in favors hi and uh the personal committee also has three other nominations for reappointment to the civil service board and those uh individuals have have been now working on on the commission for on the board for quite some time and they have expressed their willingness to continue serving on the board so we have the nomination of a Lloyd Henry for reappointment to the civil board and the nomination of Donald Palmer and Tina Darby to the civil board to the civil service board and are there any questions or comments from members of the committee regarding those nominations from council?
I was going to say the only comment I would make is I think it might make sense to move all of these
yeah at once. Okay so I'll make a motion to move those three nominations to our next council
meeting on June 10th. All in favor? Aye. I just wanted to add if I may counselor colleagues that we're very fortunate to have Lloyd Henry because he has a long time he's a retired firefighter Donald Palmer is a retired police chief and appreciation for Ms. Darby who regularly attends the civil service obstacle course training for our police officers and has made herself available to assist in those efforts so I think these are definitely folks who have shown a
commitment to the work thank you mayor for your comment thank you thank you very much counselor
please um i failed to mention this at the beginning of the meeting the next item is the finance committee and um i just want to make an announcement now that resolution 46 that appears on your agenda is being withdrawn for this meeting um there's just like some some timing issues there um so they will they will re-approach council with that when the timing is right um but we're not taking it up so therefore there's no finance committee meeting this evening and that will take us to community planning committee councillor craig thank you council president um the first item
on our on we have two items on the agenda this evening the first being the review of the historical commission recommendation for 101 south queen is there anybody from the historical
commission here to address that yes yes craig i'm happy to uh come and speak for a moment i also think uh it's ryan correct representing as a project architect too okay so you can both just
step up real quickly if you'd like great happy to have you i would like to know a little bit about
just a little bit about the project um my name is ryan griffith i'm the president of cornerstone design architects we are working with brentwood builders with our client and the developer for the property um this was the property was a it was a it's a historic hotel um but it was a blighted property uh it actually doesn't have stairs so there's no access to the third and fourth floor um without a lift um so uh the building uh was here that makes it interesting it makes it makes us it makes a survey uh something that i asked my staff to be very careful with um but uh it is a uh it's a property that um the um this is the swan hotel it is the swan hotel yeah um so it is a property that was um the convention center authority uh put on rfp um and so um and brentwood builders was the successful uh proposal for that um and so what their proposal is is that they're uh they're going to adapt to really adaptively reuse it which is just converting something to a a new use and bringing back an existing building into uh something that can uh continue to to be uh useful and preserved um and so the use would be for a 21 uh unit basically temporary in vacation rental property like an airbnb type thing yeah i don't know that it's i don't know that it's technically going to be through that service or not but that that idea so um the idea is that they want to be able to uh preserve the the corner and the and the building itself uh and then they would like to be able to uh do uh it's it's it's here because of a demolition right but the demolition component to this is uh the stairs that were removed were non-historic but there's a piece of the roof basically that's going to be the existing dormers on vine street so not one of our main facing street facing facades um that will be partially demolished in order to create uh some unit space and a roof deck um up on that the vine street side of the street so that building is not it's not that big correct
so how are we going to get 21 munich's community in there i think um ryan if i might jump in i've got a few notes here and if i uh misstate it please uh correct me um you're right council craig it's not a particularly large uh property this has been one of the challenges for the redevelopment of the site is uh it is a significant investment to do the historic rehabilitation of the building but then making the economics work of the project has been really challenging which is why it has sit um sat vacant for quite some time um this particular use for the for the site is actually a really good fit it's going to be a boutique hotel but it's a contactless hotel model um and i have in my notes here that is a total of 11 units uh for the building is that is that correct yes okay um it does make more sense than i apologize yes
i have a lot of stuff floating around in my head so i pulled after something else
okay great yes uh and i thought ryan described very well that there's just a small portion of the building that requires demolition but as a whole this historic asset is being preserved the historical commission did recommend approval I don't believe it was controversial in any way that's why we don't have anybody here from the historical commission this evening just a little more context on the site we had a zoning interpretation question earlier in the process that zoning interpretation question has been resolved the project is on a good track right now and still i need to go uh through land development i believe uh um or some portion of land development
there yeah i think there's i think that they're still waiting on land development and then we'll be working towards uh permit submission yes uh building permit submission in the next month
all right are there any questions from the committee so sorry did you say it's just going
going to be the units the 11 units there's no commercial or other component that's that's
correct so the the original take on this or concept was that there would be nine units and a small speakeasy kind of bar restaurant um the reality was is that there wasn't a great way to fit that in and yeah still get units in there um and the bigger reality and the more important thing is that there's already plenty of bars restaurants southern markets across the street there's plenty of places to eat and drink in this area of the city so yeah um it's more it's more like so it's more like supporting that having a place that is not a hotel room in your most
traditional sense to to stay yeah no i like the concept and i i just know that there was definitely interest in that but what you're saying makes a lot of sense yeah i think it would have been
a workable and fun concept, but it would have been really small scale and probably only used
by the people staying there. Right. This makes a lot of sense. Thank you. Are there any other
questions? Thank you, Councilman Craig, and thank you for being here this evening. My first question is, what happens to that parking lot in the back of the hotel? The parking lot is, I believe,
owned by the Convention Center, so it will be staying as their property. I'm not sure what
plans they might have for that they they use that um service parking lot for loading in and for um
yeah yes yeah i don't i don't i'm not aware of any anything that would be changing that
that was also one of the um uh challenges to the redevelopment of this um property was that the convention center needed to maintain that surface area parking lot in the back
And then my final question is with just 11 units, what are the rates, the nightly rates going to be in order to get a return?
That is outside of my pay grade at this point. So I'm not sure what that's going to look like. I'm sure that there's some kind of formula that they're going to use that it's, hey, it needs to compete with Airbnb as a service. It needs to compete with hotels as a service. it needs to offer something a little unique in being um in a historic building and being particularly located like it is i'm not sure what the rates are going to be i would guess i would guess that you could probably stay at the holiday holiday inn for less for example but you're not going to get a rental home by itself for something similar thing so would
these be like one to two bedroom layouts with you know diet kitchens and it is yeah yeah so
kitchenette light is kind of how it is and it is it is really it's someplace where if you could see yourself maybe visiting Lancaster for a week right and seeing the sights or being here on business or being here for a wedding or whatever that might be that it can be like kind of a touchdown space for a week maybe a little bit more so than a hotel so that's the idea and there's there's one bedrooms and then there's really cool loft spaces up and up on the the upper floor that will have access to that roof deck that's being created with part of the demolition so um I think it'll be I mean I think it's going to be unique in a lot of ways and and be offering a little bit of a different say experience than a lot of other places are
currently thank you so the Marriott will be retaining the parking lot in the back in its entirety they will yeah yeah yeah yes they will um so I think there's a fence there
now. There will be a bit of an addition that's going off of the back of this, which is going to be creating space for an elevator and stairs and lobby, and then the roof deck above the elevator and stair towers. And so by the time that gets added onto the back of the swan, if you can see when you drive past, there's a little bit of a, there's a gate beyond there, that that that uh fence is the property line so it is a small property um and they'll be they'll be
kind of backed up against a parking lot there are there any further questions from uh council as a
whole just to put a fine point on it director delfs the demolition and construction that we have before us were both deemed appropriate and meeting all the standards for the historical commission is that right yes that's correct make sure we all have that i'll have seen that in our
memo so thank you okay thank you so much um i have any questions from the public no okay i'll make a motion to move this to um full council or an attempt second all those in favor all right all right thank you thank you um the next item on our agenda is resolution number 47 authorizing submission of the community development block grant and annual action plan and i see ms geyser making her way to the table council craig yeah i could just mention to
members of council the presentation this was sent to you just before the meeting you also have it
in your inbox let's see madam mayor i think we send it to two ways and paper copies okay
i haven't covered it all but we have the headlock paper technical difficulties will not hold us
no thank you i might have enough i have more no wait these are my notes you have yours as well
it's also going to be up on the oh yeah like did you know i can also share there's more
would you like a paper copy oh they got one great great thank you
teamwork tissue thanks to boomers okay all right thank you oh Councilor Diaz, would you kindly pass these around, it's going to come up later. Good evening, Mayor, Councilors. My name is Jen Rummel, I am the Community Development Administrator within the Department of Planning and Economic Development, and I manage our Community Development Block Grants funded by the Department of Housing and Urban Development. I'm pleased to present to you tonight our 2025 fiscal year annual action plan for the utilization of our 2025 Community Block Development Grant. Before we get into the allocation details for this year, we'd like to present a brief refresher of the Community Development Block Grant program. This CDBG grant is administered by HUD and it provides annual grant entitlements to cities, and sorry go ahead oh i'm sorry that's it i'll try to keep an eye on both things that are going on the cdbg program which is administered by hud provides entitlement annual entitlement grants to states cities and counties to help develop viable urban communities by providing funding and support through the following provision of decent affordable housing the creation of a suitable living environment and the expansion of economic opportunities principally to benefit low to moderate income persons. HUD authorizes CDBG to be spent on the following eligible community development activities, and those are listed on the spreadsheet that you're looking right now. Affordable housing and preservation and production, public infrastructure improvements, public services, economic development, and planning and administration. Is yours wonky? Yeah, it's all right. next slide please okay uh you some of you may remember this from the caper presentation that we did back in i believe it was march um i'd like to give you a reminder of some of the impact that the cdbg program has had in our the last year of our five-year comp plan so uh some of the information that we captured in 2024 approximately 20 121 residents were served in 2021 we estimate that 17,000 of those people were impacted by the 11 ADA ramps that were installed in low to moderate income areas. 364 individuals were documented to have interactions with our health and housing social worker, Sonia. 422 individuals benefited from consulting with our two police social workers. 823 individuals participated in neighborhood engagement programs and that was just of the information we collected and 95.8 of those who received assistance through those that cdbg funding were low to moderate income next slide please this is just a visual of some of the partners that we work with and some of the programs that we fund so we've been lucky enough to work with uh tenfold for their health fair housing program assets for their community economic development program. SACA has been a partner of ours in helping to develop and rehabilitate affordable housing opportunities. We've also been able to fund internal programs like I mentioned before, the police social work program, the critical repair program, and the proactive housing code enforcement program, as well as supporting work in the comprehensive plan next slide please this one's really hard to see and i apologize um just a couple of demographics captured from our 2024 cdbg uh expenditures and the people that we assisted 35 identified as white 21 identified as african-american or black 37 identified as other or multiracial, and 5% declined to provide an answer. As far as ethnicity goes, 57% identified as non-Hispanic and 43% identified as Hispanic. Finally, in 2024, CDBG programming supported a majority of low to moderate income resident households, 45% or 344 from whom we collected financial data qualified as being extremely low income. 28 percent or 215 people identified as being low income and 22 percent or 168 people identified as being moderate income. So as you can see the CDBG program continues to affect the daily lives of low to moderate income city residents daily and the city continues to monitor and engage with its community members to learn and adapt to new and ongoing needs to serve the city's greatest needs so we expect to see similar results with the 2025 program and we can't wait to tell you about what we plan to do next slide please okay so on may 15 2025 the city of lancaster learned its anticipated entitlement award amount of $1.413 million, which represents a reduction of 2.59% from 2024. We're comfortable anticipating program income of $25,043, which brings our anticipated total to $1,438,690. That's the amount that we're using to plan our allocations for 2025. Unfortunately, the City fell below the threshold to receive ESG funding again this year. However, we continue to work with the Commonwealth to receive allocations for partners within our own community. The Community Development Office is looking forward to using our 2025 allocation to build upon the success we have achieved over the last four years of our comm plan. As I mentioned, our comm plan runs from 2021 to 2025. We are now in the fifth year. activities we plan to focus on supporting are strong neighborhoods safe places a sustainable economy and sound government of the mayors within the mayor's strategic plan the comp plan focus areas that strengthen neighborhood and housing expand economic opportunities and build communities and build upon the interim housing strategy to emphasize produce protect and sustain affordable housing this plan ensures that we are still able to meet our community development priorities set out in our 2021-2025 consolidated plan and we can continue to maximize community impact while minimizing any adverse budgetary impact to the general fund next slide please so taking a larger look on your spreadsheets you can see on the blue section a complete breakdown of how we plan to allocate the funds but here we're grouping them so through our extensive community engagement efforts in 2020 we identified four priorities uh that are hud eligible goals for our funding and our current goals are to maintain a quality affordable housing increase affordable i'm sorry yes increase affordable housing opportunities promote neighborhood quality of life and expand economic opportunities so in 2025 we're using the funds uh in this way 620 000 we're planning to use to develop maintain quality affordable housing 370 000 for public infrastructure improvements 182 000 for public services that improve the quality of life of our neighbors twenty thousand dollars to expand economic opportunities and two hundred and forty eight thousand dollars for planning and administration next slide please thank you bernard despite the fact that the city of lancaster has seen a successive annual reduction in cdbg resources by about two to five percent every year since the beginning of their com plan due to reduction in census data the city nonetheless is tasked with leveraging its funding to create and foster a viable resilient community to develop and implement mutually reinforcing approaches to providing housing creating quality living environments and expanding economic opportunities for the primary benefit of low to moderate city residents and households because 2025 is our the fifth year of our 2021-2025 consolidated plan earlier this year the cped team evaluated its remaining balances from previous years of the comp land and performed a comprehensive analysis of ongoing and growing community needs and as a result we brought forth in i believe it was march a substantial amendment to city council to reallocate the unspent fundings to ensure responsible and timely expenditure of cdbg funds pursuant to the city's strategic plans and the overall goals in the com plan as a result the remaining balance of 1.166 million is represented in this graph that brings us to our full funding picture of 2.605 so we are we have the ability to we want to show you what the full picture is with our carryover and with our new allocation of what are what we're able to accomplish this year um with funding so this slide provides a larger picture of what we're able to accomplish when we combine our i'm sorry next slide bernard i'm sorry uh so this shows us um a better detail of what we're able to accomplish when we combine our rollover funds with our new allocation we're proposing to allocate 1.51 million dollars to affordable housing preservation develop and development programs including the city's critical repair program the proactive housing code enforcement and affordable housing development solutions we just completed an ly process to try to help match some of our community partners with best sources of funding next we will allocate or we plan to allocate 445 000 to public infrastructure improvements by subsidizing street improvements and community projects in low to moderate income neighborhoods we are also planning to allocate 193 000 in funding to support public services which include the health and housing social worker the police social workers and the tenfold fair housing program among others we're planning to allocate forty thousand dollars to support economic development activities and providing funding to assets just a small note there their contract begins on july 1st so it's it's technically a one-year allocation but with their fiscal year beginning july 1st it's one year but it's starting later so it's it looks like two fiscal years finally we are proposing to allocate allocate 416 000 to program administration and city planning efforts uh for program projects such as the east end small area plan next slide please thank you so when combined with the rollover amounts i just wanted to show you uh that um as the city has told us and we responded more than half 58 of the funding is being allocated to maintain quality affordable housing 25 which is a combination of 17 of public services and eight percent of i'm sorry 17 public facilities and eight percent of public services is being dedicated to promote quality of life in the neighborhood two percent is being allocated to expand economic opportunities and fourteen percent is being allocated to planning and administration so this funding strategy supports goals set out in our current con plan despite a reduction in funding and reflects overall consistency with the cdbg framework that we've laid out over the last five years some additional information about um individual like the 2025 allocation and then the how it's combined into the overall location can be found on the spreadsheet on the second page of the spreadsheet that i provided next slide please if you have not had a chance to look at the annual action plan that qr code will take you directly to it So, a hard copy is still available at City Hall, and you can navigate to it also by going to the City Hall website, clicking on City Government, going down to Community Development, and then finding the draft 2025 Annual Action Plan on our website. Next slide, please. Here's a little bit of our timeline. So we were pretty proactive. Our 2025 annual action plan was posted to our website April 22nd, 2025. We have a required 30 days for posting, so we put a notice in the newspaper about a public meeting and about the AAP being available for view on April 22nd. On May 27th, more than 30 days had passed and we held our public meeting. There was no public comments received by phone, by mail, or in person. Our public comment period closed Wednesday, May 28th, and again, no public comments were
received.
Next slide, please. Just one more reminder that this is year five of five. We wanted to tell you a little bit more that we're looking forward to in community development. We are in the early stages of planning our consolidated planning process for the 2026 2030 cycles, please stay tuned for opportunities to provide feedback on how you can help to inform CDBG funding and to shape your community going forward. With that being said, I would like to open the floor to questions or comments you might have at this time. Are there questions from the
committee? Questions from council as a whole? Thank you. Thank you for the presentation. I'm always really interested in seeing how we do a little bit more or maintain with less every year and obviously the carryover amount will be really impactful how would you say that that we're impacted was this allocation impacted by most recent federal budget cuts and um will our carryover allow us to maintain particularly in um the planning and administration does that include the salaries of people who are funded who are salaries are funded by this um and will we be able to maintain them longer to do good work for our community so as as of now the reduction in
funding is solely related to a census change we were keeping an eye on announcements regularly to see when they were announced and they were uh the the cdbg allocation was announced right around the time it usually was this year. And with the amount of funding we have, we are able to continue to fund all of the internal positions. I don't think we've had to make compromises. Can you
comment on that? Have we had to make compromises? Yeah, I think from year to year, if we have had vacancies in one year, then that money would carry forward. And as long as we are administering the programs this cut was not any greater in fact it's a little bit less than we were anticipating yeah so uh that that helped so we are good through the end uh through the middle of 2026 with this budget for cdbg and then the budget the recent budget conversations at the federal level if their cdbg cuts would impact our 2026 allocation which we would find out about in march i mean sorry in may next year and then you have to make some decisions so as we go into the 2026 budget cycle for the city budget we we won't know what's happening overall with the cdbg budget the
timing is always very difficult it is yeah yeah that's something worth mentioning we did plan
ahead so yeah thank you that was thanks for asking that question that was what i wanted to know
i see a question thank you thank you counselor craig my question is um do we anticipate any rollover funds from 2025 to 2026 especially given that there's a lot of uncertainty in what funding
will look like further yeah that's a that's a very good question generally there are funds remaining we we have a requirement when we get our next year's allocation or as we're closing out 2025 we're only allowed to have one and a half times the allocation remaining so they are requiring us to continue to spend down the grant so we have to be mindful of that deadline in november simultaneously we will have money at the end of 2025 to cover at least the first six months of 2026 and often in larger pots of money for example affordable housing development solutions if there aren't partners ready and able to spend the money then we often carry that forward as well so staff vacancies and um community needs really drive the the roll over from one year until the next
thank you any further questions from council not really a question but a comment uh excellent presentation thank you jen um thank you rebecca i know your team does good work and i just want to continue to point out that like of all the things that the city could put this money towards it continues to put it into housing and i just think that that's noteworthy we all know that the affordable housing situation is difficult out there but the city continues to prioritize addressing it and i just think that's really that's a really good thing so thank you so much
okay um i'll make a motion to move this the full council and attend say again all those in favor aye aye thank you thank you thank you mayor that concludes community planning thank you so much um uh mr harris uh the last item on the
agenda is the clerk's report confirming that you've submitted that in writing to all members council yes okay thank you very much then having reached the end of our agenda i will hear a motion to adjourn all in favor aye we're adjourned thank you everybody